<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<!-- The XSL transform inserts these values as Hugo frontmatter. -->
<!-- Additionally, a "date" timestamp is inserted by the stylesheet. -->
<?title ?> 
<?linkTitle "Echomix chat user guide" ?>  <!-- Section menu link text -->
<?url "docs/chat_client/user-guide.html" ?> <!-- Required to make image links work -->
<?description ?> <!-- Optional -->
<?draft "false" ?> <!-- Optional -->
<?slug "chat" ?> <!-- Optional -->
<?layout "" ?> <!-- Optional -->
<?type "" ?> <!-- Optional -->
<?weight "1" ?> <!-- Optional -->

<!DOCTYPE article [
    <!ENTITY % shared-content SYSTEM "../../../shared-content.ent">
    %shared-content;
    <!ELEMENT xi:include (xi:fallback?) > 
    <!ATTLIST xi:include 
        xmlns:xi CDATA #FIXED "http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" 
    href CDATA #REQUIRED 
    parse (xml|text) "xml" 
    xpointer CDATA #IMPLIED 
    encoding CDATA #IMPLIED 
    accept CDATA #IMPLIED 
    accept-charset CDATA #IMPLIED 
    accept-language CDATA #IMPLIED > 
    <!ELEMENT xi:fallback ANY > 
    <!ATTLIST xi:fallback 
        xmlns:xi CDATA #FIXED "http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" > 
    <!ENTITY % local.preface.class "| xi:include"> 
    <!ENTITY % local.part.class "| xi:include"> 
    <!ENTITY % local.chapter.class "| xi:include"> 
    <!ENTITY % local.divcomponent.mix "| xi:include"> 
    <!ENTITY % local.para.char.mix "| xi:include"> 
    <!ENTITY % local.info.class "| xi:include"> 
    <!ENTITY % local.common.attrib "xml:base CDATA #IMPLIED" >
]>

<section    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
            xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1" 
            xml:id="CHANGE_ME1">
    <info>  
        <title xml:id="CHANGE_ME1.title">&chat_client; chat client user guide</title> <!-- Match to "title" or "linkTitle" promming instruction above. -->          
    </info>
    <para>This guide introduces the &chat_client; chat client. With &chat_client; you can securely
        share one-to-one and group messages with contacts. &chat_client; relies on &program_name;,
        an advanced mixnet system designed for people who have something to say, but who also value
        their anonymity. Importantly, anonymity is not the same thing as encryption, which protects
        the <emphasis>content</emphasis> of communication over the Internet. Anonymity is about
        protecting <emphasis>people</emphasis>. </para>
    <para>For technical information about how &program_name; and mixnets in general work, see
            <?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?><link
            xlink:href="sdsdsd">blah</link>. <?oxy_custom_end?>To learn more about
            <emphasis>why</emphasis> &program_name; works as it does, see <link xlink:href="sdsdsd"
            >Frequently asked questions</link> .</para>
     
    <section xml:id="CHANGE_ME2">  
        <info>  
            <title xml:id="CHANGE_ME2.title">Installing and starting &chat_client;</title>          
        </info>
        <para>The &chat_client; client is available as a Docker image or as Python code available
            from GitHub. To run it, you need a computer that runs or emulates the Linux operating
            system. (We have tested &chat_client; on <link xlink:href="https://www.debian.org/"
                >Debian </link> and <link xlink:href="https://ubuntu.com/">Ubuntu</link>.) You can
            install &chat_client; by completing one of the following procedures.</para>
        <procedure>
            <?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>
            <title>Python code procedure<?oxy_custom_end?></title>
            <para>To prepare to use the &chat_client; client source code, you need Git and Python3
                installed on your Debian or Ubuntu system. Our recommended method of building the
                application is to run it in a Python virtual environment using the Makefile included
                with the code.</para>
            <step>
                <para>Install the latest Git, Python3, and Make on your
                    system.<programlisting><prompt># </prompt><command>apt update</command>
<prompt># </prompt><command>apt install git python3 make</command></programlisting></para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Clone the &chat_client; repository at <link
                        xlink:href="https://github.com/katzenpost/katzenqt"/>. NO</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>In the <filename>katzenqt</filename> directory, create a virtual environment,
                    load additional required software, and start the client using the following
                    commands.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>
                    <programlisting><prompt>~$ </prompt><command>python3 -m venv myvenv</command>
<prompt>~$ </prompt><command>source myvenv/bin/activate</command>
<prompt>~$ </prompt><command>pip install --upgrade pip</command>
<prompt>~$ </prompt><command>pip install 'git+https://github.com/katzenpost/thin_client@a5f87b9623eb349ba376d7e7555c3154302216e8'</command>
<prompt>~$ </prompt><command>pip install -e .</command>
<prompt>~$ </prompt><command>make</command></programlisting>
                </para>
            </step>
        </procedure>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Communicating through the &chat_client; client</title>
        <para>This section describes how to configure and use &chat_client; for secure, anonymous
            communication. </para>
        <para>Like many other chat clients, &chat_client;exhibits two panes, one for contacts and
            one for messages, and a number of communication modes such as text chat, file transfer,
            and voice. The following illustration shows how &chat_client; looks when you first open
            it after installation.</para>
        <para>&chat_client; consists of a menu bar, a toolbar, two panes, and a status bar (not
            visible). The <guilabel>Conversations and contacts</guilabel> displays existing
            conversations and the contacts specific to them. The <guilabel>Messages</guilabel> pane
            displays the title of the selected conversation (if any), its messgae log, an
                <guilabel>Invite a contact</guilabel> button for adding new members, and a text box
            near the bottom for typing new messages. Buttons in the toolbar include <guilabel>New
                conversation</guilabel> (opening a dialog to configure a conversation),
                <guilabel>Accept invitation</guilabel> (opening a dialog to accept or refuse an
            invitation from another user), <guilabel>Documentation</guilabel> (activating, once
            implemented, the internal help system), and <guilabel>Quit</guilabel> (which shuts down
            the client). The tabs at the bottom of the <guilabel>Messages</guilabel> pane allow
            selection of a communication mode, with only single-line message input currrently
            implemented.</para>
        <note>
            <para>At present, only text chat works. Grayed out elements in the &chat_client;
                interface are not yet implemented.</para>
        </note>
        <para>The following screen capture shows &chat_client; as it appears when open for the first
            time.</para>
        <figure>
            <info>
                <title/>
            </info>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="pix/client-overview.jpg" scale="80"/>
                </imageobject>
                <caption>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Figure 1.</emphasis> This screen capture shows the
                        elements of the &chat_client; client interface prior to any
                        configuration.</para>
                </caption>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>Despite appearances, Katzen's emphasis on anonymity means that familiar concepts take
            on new meanings, particularly the idea of a "contact."</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Contact names are arbitrary. Contacts in one conversation are unconnected with
                    contacts in other conversations.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>&chat_client; and &program_name; operate with no information about the
                    real-world identities behind contacts. There are no e-mail addresses, telephone
                    numbers, postal addresses, or anything similar involved. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Without phone numbers or email as anchors for identity, &chat_client; users
                    require  a real-world encounters to verify who they are and to share
                    cryptographic secrets. This kind of contact bootstrapping occurs out-of-band
                    (OOB), that is, without reliance on the primary communication channel. The
                    concept is similar to the key-signing parties that PGP email users employ to
                    build a <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Web_of_trust">web of
                        trust</link>, with the difference being that encrypted email provides little
                    anonymity protection. </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>Consequently, <emphasis>conversations</emphasis> are the real organizing principle in
            &chat_client;.</para>
        <section xml:id="CHANGE_ME3">
            <info>
                <title xml:id="CHANGE_ME3.title">Creating conversations</title>
            </info>
            <para>Communication in &chat_client; takes place in the context of conversations. A
                conversation may contain just two particpants, or it may involve a large group. The
                first thing that a new user of &chat_client; must do is create a conversation. Each
                participating contact also creates a conversation.</para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">To create a conversation</emphasis></para>
            <para>
                <procedure>
                    <step>
                        <para>Open &chat_client;. Until a conversation has been created, the
                                <guilabel>Messages</guilabel> pane prompts you to create one.</para>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                        <para>In the toolbar, click the <guilabel>New conversation</guilabel>
                            button.</para>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                        <para>In the <guilabel>New conversation</guilabel> window, type a name in
                            the <guilabel>Choose conversation name</guilabel> field. This name is
                            how you identify the conversation in your own &chat_client; client. It
                            may differ from what your contacts call their corresponding
                            conversations. Click <guilabel>OK</guilabel> when finished.</para>
                        
                        <para>In the following screen capture, the <guilabel>New
                                conversation</guilabel> is being filled out.</para>
                 
                        <figure>
                            <info>
                                <title/>
                            </info>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject>
                                    <imagedata fileref="pix/client-convo-1.jpg" scale="80"/>
                                </imageobject>
                                <caption>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Figure 2.</emphasis> In this
                                        example, a user creates a first conversation called
                                            <guilabel>My first conversation</guilabel>.</para>
                                </caption>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                        <para>Type a name for yourself in the field labeled <guilabel>Choose (your)
                                name displayed to the other user(s)</guilabel>. Your contacts will
                            see this name when they accept your invitation.</para>
                        <para>In the following screen capture, a display name has been
                            provided.</para>
                        <figure>
                            <info>
                                <title/>
                            </info>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject>
                                    <imagedata fileref="pix/client-convo-2.jpg" scale="80"/>
                                </imageobject>
                                <caption>
                                    <para>The user gives her name as <guilabel>Alice</guilabel> in
                                        the context of this conversation.</para>
                                </caption>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                        <para>Click <guilabel>OK</guilabel> when finished.</para>
                        <para>Now, in the <guilabel>Conversations and contacts</guilabel> pane, the
                            name of your new conversation is displayed along with your own name. In
                            the <guilabel>Messages</guilabel> pane,
                            &chat_client;<?oxy_comment_start author="dwrob" timestamp="20251105T173304-0800" comment="This should look more like a stage direction than like a regular message."?>
                            prints a greeting message<?oxy_comment_end?>.</para>       
                        
                        <para>The final result resembles the following:</para>
                        
                        <figure>
                            <info>
                                <title/>
                            </info>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject>
                                    <imagedata fileref="pix/client-convo-3.jpg" scale="80"/>
                                </imageobject>
                                <caption>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Figure 3.</emphasis> In the
                                            <guilabel>Conversations and contacts</guilabel> pane,
                                        you can select a conversation, and the selection will be
                                        displayed in the <guilabel>Messages</guilabel> pane. You can
                                        use the <guilabel>Type to filter contacts</guilabel> text
                                        box to find a specific contact name and the conversations
                                        that contain it.</para>
                                </caption>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>
                        
                        
                        
                    </step>
                </procedure>
 
            </para>

            <para>You can create any number of conversations, each completely separate from the
                others. </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="CHANGE_ME4">
            <info>
                <title xml:id="CHANGE_ME4.title">Adding contacts to a conversation</title>
            </info>
            <para>Once you have a created a conversation, you can begin adding contacts to it. Users
                of &chat_client; have no fixed user names or passwords; instead, they bear arbitrary
                display names (which can be changed) and exert control over message streams hosted
                on the &program_name; network. To communicate with each other, contacts share their
                addresses and grant read permissions to each other. Authentication takes place once
                in the real world before communication over the mixnet begins.</para>
            <para>A user setting up a contact generates an authentication token called an
                    <emphasis>invitation</emphasis>.  The invitation is a Base64-encoded string with
                the following contents:<itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>a display name </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>a mixnet storage address that doubles as read permission  </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
            <para>The initiating user delivers the invitation OOB to one or more recipients, who
                enter the string into &chat_client; and send their own addresses and signed read
                permissions to the first user, who publishes the shared read permissions for all
                group members to see. When the process is complete, the new contact names display in
                the list of contacts for each participant in the conversation. </para>
            
            
            
            <important>
                <para>We recommend writing the invitation string on a piece paper, and presenting
                    this physically to the person whom you are inviting. The paper bearing the
                    string should be guarded carefully and destroyed once its purpose is achieved.
                    Any person gaining access to it could read all messages in the associated
                    conversation.</para>

            </important>
            <warning>
                <para>It is possible to simply send your invitation through an alternative
                    electronic channel. However, doing this degrades the &program_name; anonymity
                    protections to the level of anonymity offered by the channel that you
                    use.</para>
            </warning>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">To invite a new contact to a conversation</emphasis></para>
            <para>
                <procedure>
                    <step>
                        <para>Open &chat_client;.</para>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                        <para>With the desired conversation selected, in the
                                <guilabel>Messages</guilabel> pane on the right, click
                                <guilabel>Invite a contact</guilabel>.</para>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                        <para>In the <guilabel>Invite contact</guilabel> window, type your desired
                            display name in the field labeled <guilabel>Choose (your) name displayed
                                to the other user</guilabel>, then click
                            <guilabel>OK</guilabel>.</para>
                        <para>The following example shows the <guilabel>Invite contact</guilabel>
                            window with "Alice" specified as the issuer. </para>        
                <figure>
                    <info>
                        <title/>
                    </info>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="pix/client-invite-1.jpg" scale="80"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <caption><para><emphasis role="bold">Figure 4.</emphasis> The generated invitation string has "Alice"
                                        embedded as its creator, which is helpful to the recipient
                                        in the next steps.</para>
                        </caption>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>                        
                        
                    </step>
                    <step>
                        <para><?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>STEP
                            MISSING PENDING IMPLEMENTION<?oxy_custom_end?></para>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                        <para>Complete the invitation process by providing the invitation string
                            out-of-band to your intended contact .</para>
                    </step>
                </procedure>

            </para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">To accept an invitation that you have
                received</emphasis></para>
            <para>
                <procedure>
                    <step>
                        <para>Open &chat_client;. (In the example, our perspective shifts to Bob,
                            who is the user receiving Alice's invitation.)</para>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                        <para>In the toolbar, click <guilabel>Accept invitation</guilabel>.</para>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                        <para>In the <guilabel>Accept invitation</guilabel> window, type or paste
                            the invitation string into the field labeled <guilabel>Copy-paste the
                                invite you received</guilabel>. Your client should resemble the
                            following:</para>
                        <figure>
                            <info>
                                <title/>
                            </info>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject>
                                    <imagedata fileref="pix/client-accept-1.jpg" scale="80"/>
                                </imageobject>
                                <caption>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Figure 5.</emphasis> Bob has entered
                                        the invitation string into the <guilabel>Accept
                                            invitation</guilabel> window.</para>
                                </caption>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                        <para><?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>Missing
                            step pending implementation: Bob confirms that The expected display name
                            (Alice?) was embedded in the string.<?oxy_custom_end?></para>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                        <para><?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?><?oxy_comment_start author="dwrob" timestamp="20251108T163212-0800" comment="Note that the client currently lets me add myself on both sides of the chat." mid="5"?>Click
                                <guilabel>OK</guilabel>.<?oxy_custom_end?><?oxy_comment_end mid="5"?></para>
                    </step>
                </procedure>
            </para>
            <para>As shown below, Alice and Bob now appear in each other's contact lists, and they
                can begin exchanging messages.</para>
                <figure>
                    <info>
                        <title/>
                    </info>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="pix/client-messages-1.jpg" scale="80"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <caption><para><emphasis role="bold">Figure 6.</emphasis> Alice and Bob with their respective conversations
                            and contact lists.</para>
                        </caption>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Exchanging messages in a conversation</title>
            <para>When we look at the perspectives of Alice and Bob side-by-side, as in <emphasis
                    role="bold">Figure 6</emphasis>, a few features of &chat_client; set it apart
                from other chat clients.</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Conversations are the main organizing principle. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Contacts are members of a conversation.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="underline">Conversations</emphasis> may have any number of
                        contacts, that is, all conversations are <emphasis>groups</emphasis>.
                        One-to-one conversations are groups with exactly two members.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>The
                        conversations that you see listed are ones that you created and named.  Your
                        contacts see their own conversations that they created and named.</para>
                </listitem><?oxy_custom_end?>
                <listitem>
                    <para>When you create a conversation, you are creating and naming a
                        <?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>message
                        stream.</para>
                </listitem><?oxy_custom_end?>
                <listitem>
                    <para>You have <emphasis>write</emphasis> permissions to message streams that
                        you created; nobody else does.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Users can share <emphasis>read</emphasis> permissions to a message stream
                        with other users.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The view of a conversation that you sees in the
                            <guilabel>Messages</guilabel> pane is a virtual message log collated by
                        &chat_client; based on shared read permissions. This is how each contact
                        that is read into a conversation can see the same virtual log. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Exchanging messages in &chat_client; follows standard chat-client practice.  Alice
                and Bob see a conversation that is </para>

            
            <para/>
            
            <figure>
                <info>
                    <title>Alice sends message</title>
                </info>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="pix/client-messages-3.jpg" scale="80"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption><para>Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit, sed do eiusmod tempor incididunt ut
                            labore et dolore magna aliqua. Ut enim ad minim veniam, quis nostrud
                            exercitation ullamco laboris nisi ut aliquip ex ea commodo consequat.
                            Duis aute irure dolor in reprehenderit in voluptate velit esse cillum
                            dolore eu fugiat nulla pariatur. </para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>                       
            
            <para/>
            
            <figure>
                <info>
                    <title>Bob receives Alice's message</title>
                </info>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="pix/client-messages-4.jpg" scale="80"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption><para>Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit, sed do eiusmod tempor incididunt ut
                            labore et dolore magna aliqua. Ut enim ad minim veniam, quis nostrud
                            exercitation ullamco laboris nisi ut aliquip ex ea commodo consequat.
                            Duis aute irure dolor in reprehenderit in voluptate velit esse cillum
                            dolore eu fugiat nulla pariatur. </para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>                                  
            
            
            <para/>
            
            <figure>
                <info>
                    <title>Bob types a message to Alice</title>
                </info>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="pix/client-messages-5.jpg" scale="80"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption><para>Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit, sed do eiusmod tempor incididunt ut
                            labore et dolore magna aliqua. Ut enim ad minim veniam, quis nostrud
                            exercitation ullamco laboris nisi ut aliquip ex ea commodo consequat.
                            Duis aute irure dolor in reprehenderit in voluptate velit esse cillum
                            dolore eu fugiat nulla pariatur. </para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>                                           
            
            <para/>
            
            
            <figure>
                <info>
                    <title>Bob sends message</title>
                </info>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="pix/client-messages-6.jpg" scale="80"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption><para>Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit, sed do eiusmod tempor incididunt ut
                            labore et dolore magna aliqua. Ut enim ad minim veniam, quis nostrud
                            exercitation ullamco laboris nisi ut aliquip ex ea commodo consequat.
                            Duis aute irure dolor in reprehenderit in voluptate velit esse cillum
                            dolore eu fugiat nulla pariatur. </para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>  
                        
            <para/> 
            
            <figure>
                <info>
                    <title>Alice receives Bob's message</title>
                </info>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="pix/client-messages-7.jpg" scale="80"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption><para>Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit, sed do eiusmod tempor incididunt ut
                            labore et dolore magna aliqua. Ut enim ad minim veniam, quis nostrud
                            exercitation ullamco laboris nisi ut aliquip ex ea commodo consequat.
                            Duis aute irure dolor in reprehenderit in voluptate velit esse cillum
                            dolore eu fugiat nulla pariatur. </para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>              
            
            <para/>
            
            <figure>
                <info>
                    <title>Messaging continues</title>
                </info>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="pix/client-messages-8.jpg" scale="80"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption><para>Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit, sed do eiusmod tempor incididunt ut
                            labore et dolore magna aliqua. Ut enim ad minim veniam, quis nostrud
                            exercitation ullamco laboris nisi ut aliquip ex ea commodo consequat.
                            Duis aute irure dolor in reprehenderit in voluptate velit esse cillum
                            dolore eu fugiat nulla pariatur. </para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>                          
            
            <para/>
            
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Frequently asked questions</title>
        <para/>
        <section>
            <title>Why does anonymity matter?</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>What makes &chat_client; different from other chat clients?</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>I use an end-to-end encrypted chat service. Is that good enough?</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>What kind of users need anonymity protection?</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>I am just an ordinary person with nothing to hide. Why should I worry about being
                anonymous?</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>How does contact bootstrapping work?</title>
            <para>The following diagram details the exchange of data that takes place
                <?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>between contacts
                and the m<?oxy_custom_end?>ixnet. For more information, see <link
                    xlink:href="https://katzenpost.network/docs/specs/group_chat.html"
                    >&program_name; Group Chat Design</link>.</para>
            <figure>
                <info>
                    <title></title>
                </info>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="pix/katzen-contact-ladder.png" scale="80"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>The diagram illustrates two important aspects of the &program_name;
                            and &chat_client; security. First, the initial authentication of a
                            contact is done in a face-to-face meeting rather than electronically.
                            Second, all messaging consists of queries to the mixnet, which operates
                            somewhat like a dead-drop. Users post materials there, and other users
                            can be authorized to read those materials, but there is no direct
                            contact between users after the initial analog authentication. The
                            &chat_client; client represents these transactions in a traditional chat
                            interface, even though the mechanism does but resemble traditional
                            chat.</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>How does message exchange work?</title>
            <para><?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>TODO … a
                diagram continuing the one above.<?oxy_custom_end?></para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Why are governments and businesses so interested in my metadata?</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>What is special about a mixnet?</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Who is hosting the &program_name; servers?</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Will &chat_client; ever have audio chat, or video chat?</title>
            <para>Mixnet-based communications have high latency by design. This has little impact on
                low-bandwidth text communications, but it is very likely disqualifying for video.
                Therefore we do not plan to offer video chat. Audio, however, can be more readily
                compressed and optimized than video, and we do plan to offer video chat in the
                future. For more information see <link
                    xlink:href="https://katzenpost.network/docs/audio_eng/">Audio Engineering
                    Considerations for a Modern Mixnet</link>.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Is this legal?</title>
            <para>Let's take "this" as meaning end-to-end encryption and metadata minimization. The
                answer depends on the jurisdiction and the political weather. Countries such as
                China and Iran that attempt to exert complete and ruthless control over citizens'
                communication would probably forbid and block &chat_client; just as they do Signal
                and Tor, with a full range of possible punishments for offenders. However, Western
                democracies also enforce comprehensive surveillance over their citizens,
                particularly as a tool for law enforcement or flexibly defined "national security."
                The United States, the United Kingdom, and members of the European Union try
                constantly to expand legal surveillance and to pass laws mandating backdoors in
                encrypted devices, so far being thwarted either by public advocacy or by the
                commercial self-interest of technology vendors. Users of surveillance-resistant
                communication tools must understand the laws that apply to them, keep in mind the
                ways that those laws are stretched and broken by corrupt police, and protect
                themselves appropriately. If you knowingly violate your local laws while trusting in
                clever technology to keep you safe, remember that you must make excellent technology
                choices, use the tools perfectly, maintain operational security worthy of a
                clandestine agent, and have very good luck. In a genuinely threatening environment,
                the wisest path is often to avoid technological solutions altogether.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Why is out-of-band (OOB) secret sharing so important in &chat_client;?</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Who made &program_name; and &chat_client;?</title>
            <para>&program_name; was created by a team of programmers, cryptographers,
                mathemeticians, academics, tech industry veterans, and privacy advocates. Our
                current core contributors and past contributers are listed at <link
                    xlink:href="https://katzenpost.network/pages/team/">&program_name; Team</link>,
                and you can see who has been doing what by visiting our <link
                    xlink:href="https://github.com/katzenpost">GitHub site</link>. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>What information could authorities retrieve by seizing your computer with
                Katzen?</title>
            <para>How thorough is the local anonymization? Could e2e keys and contact identifiers be
                discovered? Is the database encrypted?</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Blah</title>
        <para>Users of conventional encrypted chat tools (Meta WhatsApp, Meta Messenger, Apple
            iMessage, Signal, etc.) may wonder, "Why should I care about that?" Many people may not
            care. However, businesses, governments, and criminals care very much about your identity
            and all of the information linked to it.</para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Internet businesses routinely harvest and sell sensitive identity data to
                        profit from invasively personalized ads and other sources.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Governments, especially law enforcement and spy agencies, collect and
                        store any data about identity, movements, employment, and political views
                        that they can get their hands on, sacrificing the privacy of millions of
                        innocent people to catch a tiny number of suspected criminals.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Actual criminals make daily use of the data they steal from these same
                        businesses and governments, enabling identity theft, credit-card fraud, and
                        blackmail.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>Consequently, &program_name; users are likely to be drawn from the following
            demographics.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>People and groups who are likely to be under surveillance by government
                    entities, including corrupt police forces and intelligence agencies.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>People facing business or government censorship.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Businesses aware of the dangers of leaking internal information to their local
                    and global competitors or to their own or other governments.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Non-profit organizations engaging in advocacy that earns them enemies in high
                    places with powerful surveillance capabilities.&chat_client_binary;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>People worried about the utter insecurity of personal data stored in both
                    cloud and on-premises databases that are accessible from the Internet.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>People who want to use the Internet for communication, but who viscerally
                    detest being the raw material that feeds <link
                        xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Surveillance_capitalism"
                        >surveillance capitalism</link>.</para>
                <para><?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>Hiding who
                    is talking to whom<?oxy_custom_end?></para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <!--    <para>The answer is apparent from the kinds of individuals and institutions who value knowledge
        of who is talking to whom. Though the law doesn't protect this kind of information very
        strongly, identifying the members of a network of people in contact with each other is often
        more useful than knowing the content of any particular conversation.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>While the <emphasis>content</emphasis> of telephone communication is shielded by
                strong limitations on wire-tapping, far weaker rules restrict the use of <link
                    xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pen_register">pen register / trap and
                    trace devices</link> to capture the identities of people engaged in private
                conversations. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>The United States Postal Service routinely photographs and stores the address
                information of mail passing through its system. The USPS <link
                    xlink:href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/federal-eye/wp/2014/11/20/postal-service-almost-never-denies-mail-surveillance-requests/"
                    >almost never</link> denies requests for this information. from <link
                    xlink:href="https://www.nytimes.com/2013/07/04/us/monitoring-of-snail-mail.html"
                    >law enforcement and others</link>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Most dramatically, US intelligence agencies use cell phone metadata (account data
                and geolocation) to target suspected terrorists for drone and missile attacks. As
                National Security Agency director Gen. Michael Hayden famously <link
                    xlink:href="https://abcnews.go.com/blogs/headlines/2014/05/ex-nsa-chief-we-kill-people-based-on-metadata"
                    >stated</link>, "We kill people based on metadata."</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>-->
        <para>And what about crime?</para>
        <para>The Namenlos network</para>
        <para><?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>Threat
            model<?oxy_custom_end?> and security guarantees.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>
                <para>Global passive adversaries (timing/correlation
                    attacks)<?oxy_custom_end?></para>
                <?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>
                <para>Second-party anonymity – why it matters<?oxy_custom_end?> …GPA can take
                    advantage of the additional metadata contacts have about other contacts.</para>
                <?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>
                <para>aim for neutrality<?oxy_custom_end?></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Encryption vs. anonymity</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Social graphs</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Dishonest service providers.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Collection of metadata – All metadata collected will eventually be seized,
                    whether by hackers, police, domestic intelligence, foreign intelligence, or
                    criminals. The only way protect data is not to possess it.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>Trade-offs</para>
        <para/>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>No live video.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Live audio still in development.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Keeping track of identities.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para/>
        <para><link
                xlink:href="https://papersplease.org/wp/2025/10/01/ice-is-buying-location-data-from-smartphone-apps-etc/"
            /></para>
        <para/>
        <para/>
        <!--            <procedure>
                <title>AppImage procedure</title>
                <step>
                    <para>Download the the AppImage package to a convenient location on your
                        computer. </para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>In a terminal, navigate to the directory containing the
                        &chat_client;-x86_64.AppImage file. Set the executable flag as
                        follows:</para>
                    <programlisting><prompt>~$ </prompt><command>chmod +x &chat_client;-x86_64.AppImage</command></programlisting>
                    <para>Note that you may need root permissions to perform this step.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>You can now start &chat_client; from a graphical file manager or directly at the
                        command line:</para>
                    <programlisting><prompt>~$ </prompt><command>./&chat_client;-x86_64.AppImage</command></programlisting>
                </step>
            </procedure>     

    <section>
        <title>Requirements for the &chat_client; chat client</title>
        <para>To use the &chat_client; chat client, you need a computer running the
            <?oxy_comment_start author="dwrob" timestamp="20251002T141316+0200" comment="Try a Mac as well."?>GNU/Linux<?oxy_comment_end?>
            operating system on x86-64 hardware. The &chat_client; software is provided as an <link
                xlink:href="https://appimage.org/">AppImage</link> package, and should run without
            problems on any modern Linux distribution, including, but not limited to, Ubuntu,
            Debian, openSUSE, CentOS, Fedora, and Arch. </para>
        <para>An AppImage package contains all of the supporting software libraries needed to run
            the included application, so there is no need to install the software directly on your
            system. However, you do need to install AppImage itself on your system before you can
            run AppImage packages. For more information,. consult the procedures for installing
            application on your Linux distribution.</para>
    </section>-->
    </section>
    
</section>
