<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<!-- The XSL transform inserts these values as Hugo frontmatter. -->
<!-- Additionally, a "date" timestamp is inserted by the stylesheet. -->
<?title ?> 
<?linkTitle "Using with NAT" ?>  <!-- Section menu link text -->
<?url "docs/admin_guide/nat.html" ?> <!-- Required to make image links work -->
<?description "" ?> <!-- Optional -->
<?draft true?> <!-- Optional -->
<?slug "" ?> <!-- Optional -->
<?layout "" ?> <!-- Optional -->
<?type "" ?> <!-- Optional -->
<?weight 40 ?> <!-- Optional -->

<!DOCTYPE article [
<!ENTITY % shared-content SYSTEM "../../../shared-content.ent">
%shared-content;
]>

<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.1" xml:id="nat">

    <info>
        <title xml:id="nat.title">Using &program_name; from behind a NAT device</title>
    </info>

    <para>&program_name; servers can be used from behind network address translation (NAT) devices.
        This applies to mix nodes, gateway nodes, service nodes, and directory authority nodes
        (dirauths). Port forwarding and other network configuration details depend on how you are
        hosting your servers and the type of router you use.</para>
    <para>Some hosting scenarios, such as the use of an AWS EC2 instance, require no manual port
        forwarding. A &program_name; node running on an EC2 instance with default network settings
        listens on its internal IP address yet can receive connections from publicly routed IP
        addresses. For home and small business routers, default policy is to block inbound
        connections from public addresses. In this scenario, you need to configure port forwarding
        to the appropriate internal IP address and port. </para>
    <para>
        <table frame="all">
            <title>Lan hosting options</title>
            <tgroup cols="5">
                <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colnum="3" colname="c3" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colnum="4" colname="c4" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colnum="5" colname="c5" colwidth="1*"/>
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry/>
                        <entry>Mix node</entry>
                        <entry>Gateway  node</entry>
                        <entry>Service node</entry>
                        <entry>Dirauth</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Transparent port forwarding (EC2, etc.)</entry>
                        <entry/>
                        <entry/>
                        <entry/>
                        <entry/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Selective forwarding (home and small business routers)</entry>
                        <entry/>
                        <entry/>
                        <entry/>
                        <entry/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Tor</entry>
                        <entry/>
                        <entry/>
                        <entry/>
                        <entry/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry/>
                        <entry/>
                        <entry/>
                        <entry/>
                        <entry/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry/>
                        <entry/>
                        <entry/>
                        <entry/>
                        <entry/>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
    </para>

    <section xml:id="tor">
        <title xml:id="tor.title">Using Tor</title>
        <para/>
        <para>Dirauth is a cooperative crash fault tolerant voting system composed of multiple
            dirauth nodes. However, each of these dirauth nodes must have knowledge of the other
            dirauth node's network connection information and public cryptographic key material.
            It's often convenient enough for dirauth operators to use a private git repo to
            coordinate changes to the dirauth configurations and public key materials. Therefore,
            dirauth operators wishing to operate a node behind a NAT device can configure their node
            to listen on a RFC1918 address such as 192.168.1.22 and yet tell the other dirauth node
            operators that their publicly routable address is some other IP address or perhaps a Tor
            Onion address. </para>
        <para/>
        <para/>
        <para>Tor: dirauths and gateways</para>
        <para>Currently, besides dirauth nodes, the only other type of node that can use Tor onion
            services are Gateway nodes, however ALL mix node types can operate behind a NAT device
            by using the BindAddresses option which tells the mix node to listen on the
            "BindAddresses" set of addresses but advertise the other set of addresses denoted by the
            "Addresses" configuration variable name. In other words, when operating nodes behind NAT
            devices, be sure to explicitly say which network interfaces to listen on via
            BindAddresses and also be explicit which addresses to advertise in the PKI document via
            Addresses. </para>
        <para>If you are configuring a Gateway node to listen on a Tor onion service, then you must
            make sure that the BindAddresses match the listening address and port in your "torrc"
            file:</para>
        <programlisting>
HiddenServiceDir /var/lib/tor/my_website/
HiddenServicePort 1234 127.0.0.1:1234
</programlisting>
        <para>We refer you to the Tor onion setup docs for more information:
            https://community.torproject.org/onion-services/setup/</para>
        <para>The corresponding Gateway config Server section might look like this:</para>
        <programlisting>
[Server]
Identifier = "gnunet"
PKISignatureScheme = "Ed25519 Sphincs+"
WireKEM = "KYBER768-X25519"
Addresses = [ "onion://your-onion-address.onion:1234"]
BindAddresses = [ "tcp://127.0.0.1:1234",]
DataDir = "/var/lib/pq-katzenpost-mixserver"
IsGatewayNode = true
IsServiceNode = false
...
</programlisting>
        <para>DIAGRAM: ROUTER, IPs, etc.</para>
        <para>mix node, device NAT device/router; Nat dev has an Internet route. Internall, mix node
            binds to an internal addrexs (show configuration). This is the same for Tor, but with
            Onion addess rahter that a static IP (see Tor and link)</para>
        <para>NATPMP STUN TURN– these are Nat PENETRATION PROTOCLDS... NOT SUPPORTED</para>
        <para>Two diagrams...Onion and IPv4/IPv6</para>
        <para>This confguration only allows for the Gateway nodes (which are also mix nodes).</para>
        <para>We need a to show an excerpt from a torrc to show where the onion listening port is
            confuigred.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="dirauths">
        <title xml:id="dirauths.title">Setting up dirauth coordination</title>

        <para/>

    </section>




</article>
