<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>title: linkTitle: &quot;Understanding Pigeonhole&quot;
  description: &quot;A high-level introduction to the Pigeonhole
  protocol for application developers&quot; categories: [&quot;&quot;]
  tags: [&quot;&quot;] author: [&quot;David Stainton&quot;] version: 0
  draft: false slug: &quot;/pigeonhole_explained/&quot;</title>
  <para>
  </para>
</section>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>Understanding Pigeonhole</title>
  <para>
    Pigeonhole is the storage layer of the Katzenpost mix network. It
    lets applications communicate anonymously using encrypted,
    append-only streams. From a passive network observer's perspective
    there is no consistent stream access and instead everything looks
    like randomly scattered queries across storage servers.
  </para>
  <programlisting>
   client      ┌───── via mix network ─────┐    courier        replicas
                                                                   ┌────┐
   kpclientd ──▶  Sphinx round-trip (×3 mix layers)  ──▶  service  │  1 │
                                                         node      ├────┤
                                                         (courier) │  2 │
                                                            │      ├────┤
                                                            └─────▶│ ...│
                                                                   └────┘
                                              fixed-throughput     K = 2
                                              connections;          replicas
                                              cannot read box IDs   per box
                                                                   (consistent
                                                                    hashing)
</programlisting>
  <para>
    For protocol details, see the
    <link xlink:href="/docs/specs/pigeonhole/">Pigeonhole
    specification</link> and sections 4-5 of the
    <link xlink:href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02933">Echomix
    paper</link>. For code, see the
    <link xlink:href="/docs/thin_client_api_reference/">API
    reference</link> and
    <link xlink:href="/docs/thin_client_howto/">how-to guide</link>.
  </para>
  <section>
    <title>Pigeonhole Streams</title>
    <para>
      All communication happens through Pigeonhole streams. A stream is
      an ordered, append-only sequence of encrypted messages, known as
      Boxes. These Boxes are stored in the storage servers using a hash
      based sharding scheme. Boxes have a fixed size maximum payload and
      are padded.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Append-only and immutable.</emphasis>
          Once a message is written to a Box, it cannot be overwritten
          by another write -- the replica rejects the second write with
          <literal>BoxAlreadyExists</literal>. New messages are appended
          at the next index. The only exception is tombstones: a
          tombstone unconditionally replaces the Box contents with an
          empty signed payload, regardless of whether the Box previously
          held data.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Single-writer,
          multi-reader.</emphasis> One writer, any number of readers.
          Two-way communication requires two streams.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Durable.</emphasis> Each message is
          replicated across multiple storage nodes. Currently, set to 2
          storage nodes per shard.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Ephemeral.</emphasis> Data is
          garbage-collected after approximately two weeks.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Unlinkable.</emphasis> Storage servers
          cannot tell which messages belong to the same stream.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Cryptographic Capabilities</title>
    <para>
      Pigeonhole is a cryptographic capability system. Access to a
      stream is controlled by two capabilities:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The <emphasis role="strong">write cap</emphasis> can write
          messages, create tombstones, and derive the read cap. Only the
          write cap holder can sign and encrypt messages, and storage
          servers verify these signatures and store the signature and
          ciphertext.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The <emphasis role="strong">read cap</emphasis> can read,
          verify signatures and decrypt messages. It cannot write or
          tombstone.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      Creating a stream produces a write cap, a read cap, and a starting
      index. The writer keeps the write cap. To grant someone read
      access, share the read cap and index with them out-of-band. That
      is the fundamental operation: <emphasis role="strong">create a
      stream, share the read cap.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
      Multiple readers can hold the same read cap independently.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>What the client daemon does</title>
    <para>
      Your application talks to a local daemon (kpclientd) through a
      thin client library. The daemon handles all cryptography (BACAP
      encryption and decryption, MKEM envelope encryption and
      decryption, signature creation and verification, payload padding
      and unpadding), Sphinx packet construction, courier selection, and
      automatic retransmission (ARQ). Your application creates streams,
      tracks indexes, and persists state for crash recovery.
    </para>
    <para>
      Most API calls are local crypto operations with no network
      traffic. Only <literal>StartResendingEncryptedMessage</literal>
      and <literal>StartResendingCopyCommand</literal> touch the
      network.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Copy commands</title>
    <para>
      Copy commands exist for when you need to atomically write more
      than one Box to one or more streams that already exist and are
      already known to other entities. The writer creates a temporary
      stream, packs all the destination writes into it, then sends a
      single copy command to a courier. The courier reads the temporary
      stream, executes all the writes to their destination streams, then
      overwrites the temporary stream with tombstones. Either all the
      destination writes succeed or none of them are visible to readers.
    </para>
    <para>
      Use cases: sending to a group, backfilling messages for an offline
      reader, atomically tombstoning old messages while writing new
      ones.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Tombstones</title>
    <para>
      A tombstone is a Pigeonhole Box which is signed with an empty
      ciphertext. Unlike normal writes, which are rejected if the Box
      already exists, a tombstone unconditionally replaces the Box
      contents. Only the write cap holder can create tombstones.
      Tombstones can be sent directly or bundled into a copy command for
      atomic deletion.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Protocol Composition</title>
    <para>
      Many different protocols can be composed using these Pigeonhole
      streams. For example, in our
      <link xlink:href="/docs/specs/group_chat">Group Chat Design</link>
      each group participant creates their own channel to write to. Each
      of the participants shares their own channel's ReadCap with the
      other group members. Therefore each group member monitors and
      reads from all the other channels in the group. Each of them can
      simply write to their own channel in order to write a message to
      the group.
    </para>
    <para>
      Fundamentally, protocols are composed by creating channels and
      sharing the read caps to those channels. When writing to a channel
      the entity doing the writing must keep track of the current index
      into the channel. This is the reason why channels are single
      writer, multi reader; because without coordination, multiple
      writers would be racing to write first before any of the others
      write to a specific index.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
