<para>
  --- title: linkTitle: &quot;Threat Model&quot; draft: false slug:
  &quot;/threat_model/&quot; author: [&quot;David Stainton&quot;,
  &quot;Eva Infeld&quot;] ---
</para>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="threat-model">
  <title>Threat Model</title>
  <para>
  </para>
</section>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="the-purpose-and-structure-of-this-document">
  <title>The purpose and structure of this document</title>
  <para>
    This threat model document is unique in the privacy technology
    landscape for its detailed treatment of realistic adversary
    capabilities. It is not a description of a superficial, theoretical
    system, but rather of complex, real-life software that is being
    interrogated and constantly re-designed to provide the best possible
    security. We examine it from the point of view of both theoretical
    design, networking choices and practical pitfalls.
  </para>
  <para>
    And still, it is not and will likely never be comprehensive. Various
    attacks and countermeasure strategies will be added to this document
    in the future, as it keeps evolving. However, we feel that it
    already provides a valuable, systematic view of the challenges faced
    by mixnet technology.
  </para>
  <para>
    There exists a rich body of academic work analyzing how one might
    disrupt the functioning of a Mixnet or circumvent its security and
    privacy guarantees. We have endeavored to compile these decades
    research and summarized these attacks in the table on page 3. The
    table on page 4 focuses on networking security threats that are
    specific to Katzenpost protocol choices.
  </para>
  <para>
    We then delve into the countermeasures employed by Katzenpost and
    discuss their efficacy. A special care is taken to discuss the
    details of post-quantum cryptographic primitives that we have
    introduced in several places of the design.
  </para>
</section>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="introducing-the-adversary">
  <title>Introducing the adversary</title>
  <para>
    It is no longer controversial to say that in the modern world, we
    face incredibly powerful surveillance adversaries. These could be
    state, corporate or criminal actors, vying for our information to
    use as means of making profit, manipulating us and others, gaining
    leverage, strengthening their authority, or as means of persecution.
    In many contexts, we have little hope for non-technical solutions
    due to lack of sufficiently powerful pressure in favor of privacy.
  </para>
  <para>
    And so in a quest for technical solutions, we need equally powerful
    tools. In the case of communication tools, the Internet’s bread and
    butter, we would like to allow users to interact and exchange
    information with reasonable expectation of both the content and
    metadata of their communication, and personal information such as a
    user’s social graph, being protected from such adversaries.
    Therefore, we consider an adversary capable of the following:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        The adversary can see the connections of the entire global
        internet and is capable of intricate statistical analysis of
        gathered data.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        The adversary can disable parts of the network.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        The adversary can plant or take over some devices in the network
        to inject malicious code and manipulate the functioning of the
        network or to gain access to the information available to them.
        The takeover could happen by technical means or by exercising
        force outside of the network.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        The adversary has very large (but not infinite) computational
        resources, and is capable of cryptanalysis on par with frontier
        research.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        The adversary has access to a quantum computer, or will have
        access to a quantum computer in the near future.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        The adversary can supplement collected data with rich context of
        already gathered data on all users from other sources.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
    If we hope for our work to be relevant in the modern world, we can
    no longer settle for weak threat models. That is the bar we set for
    ourselves at Katzenpost.
  </para>
</section>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="katzenpost-mixnet-threat-model-summary">
  <title>Katzenpost mixnet threat model summary</title>
<literallayout>Firstly, assumptions about the user:
</literallayout>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        The user acts reasonably and in good faith.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        The user obtains an authentic copy of the Katzenpost client and
        the mixnet client configuration file.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
<literallayout>Secondly, assumptions about the user’s computer:
</literallayout>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        The computer operates correctly and is not compromised by
        malware.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
<literallayout>Thirdly, assumptions about the mixnet:
</literallayout>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        The mixnet only provides internal services and does not have any
        &quot;exit nodes&quot; or anything that resembles a proxy
        service or VPN.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        All mixnet protocols are protocols which do not force
        interaction.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        All mixnet protocols are low bandwidth and latency tolerant.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
<literallayout>Finally, assumptions about the world:
The three core protocols of Katzenpost are configured to use modern cryptographic primitives which are valid and considered impossible to break, for example:</literallayout>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        PKI Signature Scheme using Edd25519-Sphincs+
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        NIKE Sphinx using X25519
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        PQ Noise with pqXX pattern using Xwing
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
<literallayout>What the user’s Gateway can achieve keeping in mind that typically a fair sized mixnet will have more than one gateway node:
</literallayout>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        A Gateway node learns when a given client is online.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        A Gateway node learns the client’s IP address.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        A Gateway node learns how many messages the client sends and
        receives.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        A Gateway node does NOT learn the sent message destinations or
        the received message origins.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        A Gateway node does NOT learn if a given sent or received
        message is a decoy or not.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        A Gateway node can drop or corrupt any sent or received message.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        A Gateway node can spam a user with invalid messages.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        A Gateway node can duplicate old messages. However duplicate
        outbound messages will be dropped by the first hop as per Sphinx
        packet deduplication cache.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
<literallayout>What a sufficiently global, passive adversary can achieve:
</literallayout>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        A GPA can learn who is using the mixnet and where their Gateway
        nodes are located.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
<literallayout>What a local network attacker can achieve:
</literallayout>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        A local network can observe when a user is using Katzenpost.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        A local network can block Katzenpost.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
<literallayout>What a compromise of the user’s computer can achieve:
After an endpoint device is compromised, an attacker can impersonate that user, receiving and sending messages. The attacker does NOT learn the communication correspondent network locations.</literallayout>
<literallayout>What a Service Node can achieve:
A Service Node on the mix network does not know from whence it’s service request message came. Therefore in general, absent some clever attack, the Service Nodes learn nothing about the clients that interact with them.</literallayout>
<literallayout>What a contact can achieve:
</literallayout>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        A contact can spam a user with messages.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        A contact can, to some extent, prove to a third-party that a
        message came from a user
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        A contact can retain messages from a user, forever.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
<literallayout>What a random person on the Internet can achieve:
A random person can attempt to DoS the mix network or a specific service on the mixnet.</literallayout>
</section>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="a-summary-of-theoretical-security-concerns-in-a-mixnet">
  <title>A summary of theoretical security concerns in a Mixnet</title>
  <informaltable>
    <tgroup cols="3">
      <colspec align="left" />
      <colspec align="left" />
      <colspec align="left" />
      <thead>
        <row>
          <entry>
            <emphasis role="strong">Mixnet attack type</emphasis>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <emphasis role="strong">Attack description</emphasis>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <emphasis role="strong">Necessary adversary
            capabilities</emphasis>
          </entry>
        </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry>
            Intersection, Statistical Disclosure Attacks
          </entry>
          <entry>
            Over time, adversary can glean statistical information that
            makes the probability distribution of who Alice is
            communicating with non-uniform. Law of Large Numbers implies
            the anonymity set tends to the set of clients with identical
            probability in the long run to the actual recipient.
          </entry>
          <entry>
            The adversary must typically be able to see messages
            entering and leaving the network. This is customarily
            treated as a PGA, despite only requiring a view of the
            network’s perimeter. The adversary must be able to
            distinguish messages from dummy traffic, or observe when
            users are active.
          </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>
            <emphasis>n</emphasis> − 1 Attack
          </entry>
          <entry>
            The adversary causes the mix to contain only messages sent
            by the adversary, except one. In the context of continuous
            time mixing such as with the Poisson mix, this means that
            the adversary drops or delays other messages until the mix
            is empty before the target message enters the mix. The
            adversary sees the target message exit the mix to its next
            destination.
          </entry>
          <entry>
            The adversary must compromise routers which are upstream
            from a target mix node so as to be able to block incoming
            messages, send messages, as well as be able to tell when a
            target message passes through them.
          </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>
            Epistemic Attack
          </entry>
          <entry>
            The fact that a client is issued only a subset of the mix
            nodes’ directory and encryption keys can leak information to
            the adversary.
          </entry>
          <entry>
            The adversary has knowledge of the target client’s view of
            the network which distinguishes them among clients. This
            could happen via a zero day or a design flaw such as not
            implementing PIR for discovery.
          </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>
            Denial of Service Attack
          </entry>
          <entry>
            The adversary is able to disrupt the functioning of the
            service, often by overwhelming its resources.
          </entry>
          <entry>
            The adversary has sufficient network and computational
            resources to overwhelm the network.
          </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>
            Sybil Attack
          </entry>
          <entry>
            The adversary plants a large number of malicious nodes, and
            is therefore able to glean partial or complete information
            to follow a message through the mix and disrupt the network.
          </entry>
          <entry>
            The adversary has sufficient resources to take over the
            network, and the network’s design allows for the creation of
            a large number of malicious nodes.
          </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>
            Compulsion Attack
          </entry>
          <entry>
            The adversary compels enough honest node operators to
            disclose information to follow a message through the mix
            network .
          </entry>
          <entry>
            The adversary has the necessary force to compel a sufficient
            number of honest actors to do the adversary’s bidding.
          </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>
            Timing Attack
          </entry>
          <entry>
            An active adversary manipulates the timing of the packets
            passing through compromised routers, or passive adversary
            exploits timing information that is leaked despite padding.
          </entry>
          <entry>
            The passive attack could happen via a zero day or design
            flaw. The efficacy of the active attack needs to be analyzed
            with respect to the specific design.
          </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>
            Cryptographic Attacks
          </entry>
          <entry>
            The adversary is able to forge a signature, generate a
            second hash preimage, decrypt ciphertext or do other damage
            assumed to be prevented by the use of cryptography.
          </entry>
          <entry>
            The adversary can break the security of one or more
            cryptographic primitives through a cryptographic zero day or
            sufficient computational resources, or exploit a flaw in
            their implementation.
          </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>
            Endpoint Security Attacks
          </entry>
          <entry>
            The adversary breaches the security of a user’s device via
            an attack not directly related to the mixnet.
          </entry>
          <entry>
            The adversary is able to exploit a technical flaw in the
            user’s device or compel the user to grant him access.
          </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>
            Predecessor Attack
          </entry>
          <entry>
            The adversary compromises at least one mix node in each
            routing topology layer. Eventually a client will randomly
            select a bad route where every mix node in the route is
            compromised.
          </entry>
          <entry>
            The adversary must have the capability to operate or
            compromise mix nodes, at least one in each routing topology
            layer. See countermeasure section for more details.
          </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>
          </entry>
          <entry>
          </entry>
          <entry>
          </entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </informaltable>
</section>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="networking-security-concerns-in-katzenpost">
  <title>Networking security concerns in Katzenpost</title>
  <informaltable>
    <tgroup cols="3">
      <colspec align="left" />
      <colspec align="left" />
      <colspec align="left" />
      <thead>
        <row>
          <entry>
            <emphasis role="strong">Mixnet attack type</emphasis>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <emphasis role="strong">Attack description</emphasis>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <emphasis role="strong">Necessary adversary
            capabilities</emphasis>
          </entry>
        </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry>
            Tagging Attack
          </entry>
          <entry>
            The adversary exploits some kind of cryptographic
            malleability property of the Sphinx packet format in order
            to violate the privacy notions of the mix network.
          </entry>
          <entry>
            The adversary must be able to witness the Sphinx payload
            decryption to determine if it was tagged or not. This means
            compromising a Provider for forward packets and compromising
            a client’s endpoint device for SURB replies.
          </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>
            Replay Confirmation Attack
          </entry>
          <entry>
            If a Sphinx packet is able to be replayed then the adversary
            may send the packet many times concurrently in order to
            observe the traffic burst in another part of the network.
          </entry>
          <entry>
            The mix nodes maintain Sphinx replay caches in order to
            prevent replays; the attack is therefore only possible if
            there is a replay cache malfunction.
          </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>
            SURB Confirmation Attack
          </entry>
          <entry>
            If a client sends many
            SURBs<link linkend="fn1" id="fnref1" role="footnote-ref"><superscript>1</superscript></link>
            to another entity on the network, that entity may choose to
            send out ALL the SURBs at once in order to observe the
            traffic burst in another part of the network.
          </entry>
          <entry>
            The adversary is a global passive observer of the network
            and participant in the network; additionally the adversary
            must be in possession of multiple SURBs created by another
            entity on the network.
          </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>
            ARQ Confirmation Attack
          </entry>
          <entry>
            The adversary’s goal is to find a specific
            ARQ<link linkend="fn2" id="fnref2" role="footnote-ref"><superscript>2</superscript></link>
            client who is currently interacting on the network by
            causing targeted outages of entry Providers after the target
            service receives a protocol message. To start, half of the
            entry Providers are allowed to receive messages. If the
            adversary observes a retransmission then it confirms the
            client is in the group of entry Providers that we blocked
            messages to. The adversary continues the binary search and
            finds the client’s entry Provider in log(n) time.
          </entry>
          <entry>
            The adversary must have access to a target mixnet service so
            as to distinguish a message transmission versus a
            retransmission. The adversary must also be able block
            messages from going to specific mixnet nodes, in this
            example, entry Providers.
          </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>
          </entry>
          <entry>
          </entry>
          <entry>
          </entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </informaltable>
</section>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="attack-countermeasures">
  <title>Attack Countermeasures</title>
  <para>
    Here we describe the attack countermeasures currently used by the
    Katzenpost mix network software design.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="intersection-attacks">
    <title>Intersection Attacks</title>
    <section xml:id="attack-description">
      <title>Attack description:</title>
<literallayout>Intersection attacks, also known as long term statistical disclosure attacks have two basic categories:
</literallayout>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The Adversary learns to whom Alice sends messages.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The Adversary learns who sends Alice messages.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section">
      <title></title>
      <para>
        Statistical disclosure attacks work to some extent on all
        anonymous communication networks. The Katzenpost client and
        Katzen messaging protocol is designed to provide partial defense
        against long-term intersection attacks as well as sufficient
        defence against short-term timing correlation attacks.
      </para>
      <para>
        The simplest form of this attack assumes a global passive
        adversary who watches Alice’s interactions with the mix network.
        Whenever Alice sends a message, a set of potential recipients
        are noted by observing which clients receive a message shortly
        after Alice sends her message. After many hours, days or weeks
        of noting these sets of potential recipients, an intersection
        among these sets may reveal the set of recipients Alice sends
        messages to.
      </para>
      <para>
        The classical mix network literature has described intersection
        attacks in terms of a mix network where a passive network
        observer can watch individual clients receive messages. This
        assumption can be otherwise stated that the adversary observes
        all the inputs and outputs of the mix network and thus receives
        a high granularity of statistical information.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="countermeasure">
      <title>countermeasure</title>
      <para>
        Katzenpost and the Katzen messaging protocol are designed to
        provide partial defense against intersection attacks. Complete
        defense is not practical because user behavior is often
        repetitive and they cannot stay connected to the mixnet forever.
        Attack success depends largely on the adversary’s ability to
        predict user behavior. If user’s behavior is overly repetitive
        this may lead to the success of such attacks.
      </para>
<literallayout>Although the Katzenpost continuous time mixing strategy provides defense against short term timing correlation attacks, additional defense mechanisms are required to defend against longer term attacks:
</literallayout>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            async message queueing and retrieval at the network edge
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            traffic padded message retrieval
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            loop decoy traffic
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            uniform traffic patterns (all sent messages result in a SURB
            reply)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section-1">
      <title></title>
      <para>
        The Katzenpost chat protocol known as Katzen, uses an additional
        network route to provide another indirection to protect the
        network location of clients. In other words, while Katzen
        clients connect to the mixnet using a randomly selected entry
        Provider, they retrieve messages from a different Provider mix
        node on the network; message retrieval is done by means of a
        Sphinx SURB, single use reply block which is sent to the
        messaging queue service so that a reply containing a message
        payload can be sent back to the client, anonymously. All sent
        messages result in a SURB reply being sent back to the client.
      </para>
      <para>
        Katzenpost clients periodically send loop decoy messages; these
        Sphinx packets are sent to a randomly selected Provider whose
        echo service sends the client’s packet payload back to the
        client via the attached SURB. However, loop decoy messages are
        only distinguishable from normal messages to the client that
        receives them. Passive network observers will not be able to
        tell the difference. These decoy loops are uniformly distributed
        among all of the Providers (AKA service/exit mix nodes).
      </para>
      <para>
        Whenever clients retrieve messages from their locally connected
        entry Provider, they do so using a traffic padded protocol that
        either sends them 0 or 1 message where both outcomes are
        indistinguishable from the perspective of a passive network
        observer.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="n-1-attacks">
    <title><emphasis>n</emphasis> − 1 Attacks</title>
    <section xml:id="attack-description-1">
      <title>attack description:</title>
      <para>
        An <emphasis>n</emphasis> − 1 attack is a multi stage attack
        where the adversary observes a target message enter the mixnet
        and must perform the attack in order to follow the message to
        the next hop. The <emphasis>n</emphasis> − 1 attack is performed
        repeatedly for each hop in the route in order to discover the
        final destination.
      </para>
      <para>
        Although the adversary could simply compromise each mix node in
        the route starting with the first hop, that is the compulsion
        attack category and is a distinct attack category from the
        <emphasis>n</emphasis> − 1 attack category. The
        <emphasis>n</emphasis> − 1 attack is performed by the adversary
        compromising upstream routers so that they have the capability
        of watching messages enter the target mix, blocking any of those
        messages if they choose to, and sending messages of their own
        into the target mix node. By using these capabilities the
        adversary is able to manipulate mix nodes so that they only
        contain the target message and messages sent by the adversary.
      </para>
      <para>
        For a good introduction to <emphasis>n</emphasis> − 1 attacks,
        please see . In the context of continuous time mixing strategies
        like &quot;Stop and Go&quot; and Poisson , the
        <emphasis>n</emphasis> − 1 attack is performed by the adversary
        blocking or delaying (although delaying obviously wouldn’t work
        for Stop and Go) incoming messages ahead of time so that they
        are reasonably certain the mix is empty before the target
        message enters the mix.
      </para>
      <para>
        When the target message enters the empty mix, it is artificially
        delayed by the mixing strategy and then routed to the next hop.
        The adversary gets to observe where the message is going for
        it’s next hop because they are reasonably sure that the message
        exiting the mix, although it is bitwise unlinkable because of
        the cryptographic transformation, it must be the same message.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="countermeasure-1">
      <title>countermeasure</title>
      <para>
        : Katzenpost currently does not have any countermeasures in
        place for <emphasis>n</emphasis> − 1 attacks. See Future
        Countermeasures section below.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="epistemic-attack-route-fingerprinting">
    <title>Epistemic Attack: route fingerprinting</title>
    <section xml:id="attack-description-2">
      <title>attack description:</title>
      <para>
        A route fingerprinting attack is when the adversary is able to
        identify a client by the specific route being used.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="countermeasure-2">
      <title>countermeasure:</title>
      <para>
        Katzenpost doesn’t allow clients to have a partial view of the
        network. The directory authority system publishes the full
        network view to be cached by the edge nodes, Providers, so that
        clients can retrieve them.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="denial-of-service">
    <title>Denial of Service</title>
    <section xml:id="attack-description-3">
      <title>attack description:</title>
      <para>
        Sending many packets into the mix network can cause the mix
        nodes to become overwhelmed and begin dropping packets. The
        logical conclusion to this scenario is that there is effectively
        a network outage until the adversary stops sending so much
        traffic.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="countermeasure-3">
      <title>countermeasure:</title>
      <para>
        Rate limiting individual clients is the current countermeasure.
        However this only stops the DOS attack from being conducted by a
        single client entity. However the adversary could still DOS the
        network by using many clients to send packets.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sybil-attack">
    <title>Sybil Attack</title>
    <section xml:id="attack-description-4">
      <title>attack description:</title>
      <para>
        The adversary plants a large number of malicious nodes, and is
        therefore able to glean partial or complete information to
        follow a message through the mix network.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="countermeasure-4">
      <title>countermeasure:</title>
      <para>
        We mitigate Sybil attacks by preventing mix nodes from
        automatically joining the network. A prerequisite for joining
        the network is to have all the directory authorities add the new
        mix node’s connection information and public cryptographic key
        material to their configuration. Please see the Future
        Countermeasures section below for a discussion of additional
        directory authority features including a reputation system.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="compulsion-attack">
    <title>Compulsion Attack</title>
    <section xml:id="attack-description-5">
      <title>attack description:</title>
      <para>
        The adversary compels enough honest node operators to disclose
        information to follow a message through the mix network.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="countermeasure-5">
      <title>countermeasure:</title>
      <para>
        Our current countermeasure for the compulsion attack is frequent
        mix key rotation, every 20 minutes. See Future Countermeasures
        section below.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="timing-attacks">
    <title>Timing Attacks</title>
    <section xml:id="attack-description-6">
      <title>attack description:</title>
      <para>
        An active adversary manipulates the timing of the packets
        passing through compromised routers, or passive adversary
        exploits timing information that is leaked despite padding.
      </para>
      <para>
        Currently, there are no known timing attacks against any
        Katzenpost protocols. Timing correlation attacks are already
        covered in the intersection attack category. And although all
        mix network protocols leak statistical information no matter
        what countermeasures are used, we posit that this leaked
        statistical information isn’t really the same thing as
        traditional timing attacks against a cryptographic system. In
        fact, the mix network is actively preventing timing attacks
        injecting latency into the system.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="countermeasure-6">
      <title>countermeasure:</title>
      <para>
        No known timing attacks and therefore no countermeasure.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="cryptographic-attacks">
    <title>Cryptographic Attacks</title>
    <section xml:id="attack-description-7">
      <title>attack description:</title>
      <para>
        There are no known cryptographic attacks against Katzenpost core
        protocols (sphinx, noise, dirauth). However we explore
        theoretical cryptographic attacks in the Cryptographic Protocols
        section below.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="countermeasure-7">
      <title>countermeasure:</title>
      <para>
        All core Katzenpost protocols make use of hybrid post quantum
        cryptographic constructions which in theory protect against
        active quantum adversaries.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="endpoint-security-attacks">
    <title>Endpoint Security Attacks</title>
    <section xml:id="attack-description-8">
      <title>attack description:</title>
      <para>
        The adversary breaches the security of a user’s device via an
        attack not directly related to the mixnet.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="countermeasure-8">
      <title>countermeasure:</title>
      <para>
        There are no countermeasures provided by Katzenpost for endpoint
        security because it’s considered an orthogonal concern.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="tagging-attack">
    <title>Tagging Attack</title>
    <section xml:id="attack-description-9">
      <title>attack description:</title>
      <para>
        The Sphinx cryptographic packet format allows for a one bit
        tagging attack under certain circumstances. The reason for
        allowing the design to have this security defect is to allow for
        the Single Use Reply Block. The Sphinx header is MAC’ed but the
        packet body is not. Instead, the body is encrypted with a
        wide-block cipher (an SPRP). This ensures that an expected
        verification block in the beginning of the plaintext can be used
        to verify the plaintext in the final decryption. If a bit in the
        payload ciphertext gets flipped then the payload decryption will
        yield garbled results and the expected verification block will
        not be present. Therefore in order to make use of this to
        perform a tagging attack, the adversary must have access to the
        result of the payload decryption as well as the ability to tag
        the packet some number of hops earlier in the route. We call
        this a one bit tagging attack because it yield one bit of
        information: Either the verification block was destroyed or not.
      </para>
      <para>
        In Katzenpost there are two ways to use Sphinx to send a
        payload. Forwards packets and SURB reply packets. Both of these
        Sphinx packet types are susceptible to a one bit tagging attack:
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="tagging-attack-against-forward-sphinx-packets">
      <title>tagging attack against forward Sphinx packets:</title>
      <para>
        Clients send forwards Sphinx packets to mixnet services which
        reply via a SURB in the payload. Let’s say an adversary
        &quot;tags&quot; a forward Sphinx packet sent by Alice. The
        adversary would have to compromise or collude with the service
        Providers on the mixnet in order to witness the forward packet
        payload decryption failure which indicates the tag.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="tagging-attack-against-surb-replay-sphinx-packets">
      <title>tagging attack against SURB replay Sphinx packets:</title>
      <para>
        If an adversary &quot;tags&quot; a SURB reply which a mixnet
        service sends to a client, then only the client will be able to
        witness the packet payload decryption failure. The adversary
        would have to compromise the client’s endpoint device to witness
        this event (or to compromise the key materials allowing them to
        compute the failed payload decryption themselves).
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="countermeasure-9">
      <title>countermeasure:</title>
      <para>
        In the context of a forward Sphinx tagging attack on Katzenpost,
        the adversary must compromise or collude with the destination
        service Provider. If that’s the case then attack allows the
        adversary to learn which Provider node and service the packets
        was destined for. Although this is valuable information in the
        context of the current Katzen protocol, see the Future
        Countermeasures section below for a discussion of how we plan to
        mitigate intersection attacks in the future because it also
        carries over to much greater defense against this forward
        payload tagging attack.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="countermeasure-10">
      <title>countermeasure:</title>
      <para>
        We could encode the last hop’s Sphinx routing command, inside
        the Sphinx payload instead of the header. This would provide
        short term plausible deniability in the sense that an adversary
        conducting a tagging attack would be destroying the routing
        information so that they cannot know if the packet was a decoy
        or not.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="replay-confirmation-attack">
    <title>Replay Confirmation Attack</title>
    <section xml:id="attack-description-10">
      <title>attack description:</title>
      <para>
        If a Sphinx packet were allowed to be replayed then the
        adversary may send the packet many times concurrently in order
        to observe the traffic burst in another section of the network.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="countermeasure-11">
      <title>countermeasure:</title>
      <para>
        Katzenpost mix nodes maintain a relay cache which prevents
        Sphinx packets from being replayed. This cache doesn’t grow
        forever since it’s only kept until the end of the epoch which
        are currently only a 20 minute duration.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="surb-confirmation-attack">
    <title>SURB Confirmation Attack</title>
    <section xml:id="attack-description-11">
      <title>attack description:</title>
      <para>
        If a client sends many SURBs to another entity on the network,
        that entity may choose to send out ALL the SURBs at once in
        order to observe the traffic burst in another part of the
        network. This works as an entry node discovery attack.
      </para>
      <para>
        Although currently, all Katzenpost protocols only send one SURB
        at a time, this attack still applies if the adversary
        accumulates enough SURBs to form a visible traffic burst within
        the mix network.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="countermeasure-12">
      <title>countermeasure:</title>
      <para>
        No countermeasure. See Future Attack Countermeasure section
        below for the discussion of how to countermeasure this attack.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="arq-confirmation-attack">
    <title>ARQ Confirmation Attack</title>
    <section xml:id="attack-description-12">
      <title>attack description:</title>
      <para>
        See above table entry for ARQ confirmation attack description.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="countermeasure-13">
      <title>countermeasure:</title>
      <para>
        Currently, no countermeasure.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="predecessor-attack">
    <title>Predecessor Attack</title>
    <section xml:id="attack-description-13">
      <title>attack description:</title>
      <para>
        A bad route is defined as a route in which every node is
        compromised. The goal of such an attack is to link a given
        client with a specific destination or service on the destination
        node. This attack is also known as the Predecessor Attack and is
        detailed in with many variations for all the different types of
        anonymous communication networks. In the context of the
        Katzenpost mixnet, the Predecessor Attack is performed by the
        adversary compromising at least one node in each routing
        topology layer. Clients using the mixnet will eventually select
        a bad route.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="countermeasure-14">
      <title>countermeasure:</title>
      <para>
        Fundamentally, we have two choices, either we have clients
        select a new route for each message sent or they select one
        route and use that for some time duration. In the former, every
        time a message is sent, the probability of selecting a bad route
        is increased. Whilst in the later, if a client selects a bad
        route they use it many times, but the probability of selecting a
        bad route is reduced.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="section-2">
      <title></title>
      <para>
        Yet another countermeasure is to design the mixnet protocols
        such that they use a new destination for each message using some
        kind of private deterministic permutation achieving a uniform
        distribution of message amongst the destination mixnet nodes and
        their message slots. We have chosen this last countermeasure for
        Katzenpost and it will be detailed elsewhere in our literature.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="future-countermeasures">
  <title>Future Countermeasures</title>
  <section xml:id="intersection-attacks-1">
    <title>Intersection Attacks</title>
    <section xml:id="section-3">
      <title></title>
      <para>
        The new Katzen protocol is sometimes referred to as scatter
        queue. Two communicating parties each exchange shared secrets
        which they use to determine a new &quot;mailbox&quot; for each
        message. To be clear, this new protocol is an improved revision
        of the previous Katzen protocol where each party chooses their
        own &quot;mailbox&quot; (queue Provider + queue ID); the
        difference here is that instead of the two parties exchanging
        mailbox locations they exchange seeds which are used to
        deterministically generate mailbox locations for each message.
      </para>
      <para>
        This new protocol still uses all four previously mentioned
        mechanisms to achieve countermeasure against intersection
        attacks however the new &quot;scatter queue&quot; design
        drastically reduces the amount of metadata which can be
        collected by the operators of the mailbox Provider mix nodes. We
        think this is a huge improvement to the threat model. But it
        would be great if we could quantify the improvement using
        various anonymity metrics. Firstly, Shannon entropy seems
        applicable here because we can make statements like
        &quot;compared to the old protocol, scatter queue increases the
        entropy on Providers where malicious adversaries are trying to
        correlate communicating party sets with messages arriving at
        specific mailboxes&quot;; the new protocol makes this
        infeasible.
      </para>
<literallayout>Therefore we can say that the new Katzen messaging protocol mitigates or partially mitigates intersection attacks by means of five mechanisms:
</literallayout>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            async message queueing and retrieval at the network edge
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            traffic padded message retrieval
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            loop decoy traffic
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            uniform traffic patterns (all sent messages result in a SURB
            reply)
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            scatter queue
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="n-1-attacks-1">
    <title><emphasis>n</emphasis> − 1 Attacks</title>
    <section xml:id="section-4">
      <title></title>
      <para>
        Here we will attempt to describe a partial countermeasure
        wherein clients receive statistical information from the network
        which is cryptographically signed by it’s authors. Client use
        this data to decide if there’s an ongoing
        <emphasis>n</emphasis> − 1 attack, if there is they disconnect
        from the network and try again later.
      </para>
      <para>
        There are two sources of information about
        <emphasis>n</emphasis> − 1 attacks:
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            mix loops
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            client loops
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="mix-loops-vs-client-loops">
      <title>Mix loops vs client loops</title>
      <para>
        In theory mix loops can detect <emphasis>n</emphasis> − 1
        attacks in the context of a continuous time mix. Such an attack
        means the adversary is dropping or delaying messages before they
        enter the mix. Therefore the mix originating loop decoy message
        can function as a sort of heartbeat protocol that allow the mix
        to detect <emphasis>n</emphasis> − 1 attacks. Obviously this mix
        loop decoy message might get dropped by the network for various
        reasons that have nothing to do with an
        <emphasis>n</emphasis> − 1 attack. The red green blue heartbeat
        mixnet paper (by george) suggests the countermeasure of the
        individual mixes halting their routing of messages temporarily
        to thwart the <emphasis>n</emphasis> − 1 attacks. This would
        work but it would also probably create unnecessary outages.
        Instead we want a system that let’s the client software decide
        whether or not there is an ongoing <emphasis>n</emphasis> − 1
        attack. Clients can also detect such attacks with their own end
        to end loop decoy messages. However we want the mixes to publish
        a signed certificate containing their mix loop statistics.
        Client will then download these mix loop statistics from the
        providers and they will use those statistics along with their
        own client loop statistics to make decisions with regards to
        <emphasis>n</emphasis> − 1 network status.
      </para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">TODO: add detailed description of client
        heuristics for deciding if there’s an n-1 attack</emphasis>
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="core-cryptographic-protocols">
  <title>Core Cryptographic Protocols</title>
<literallayout>Katzenpost consists of three cryptographic protocols:
</literallayout>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        PKI/Dirauth
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        PQ Noise
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Sphinx
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>
    Katzenpost is an overlay network meaning that we aren’t trying to
    replace IP (internet protocol). Overlay means we build protocol
    layers that sit on top of existing Internet protocols. Currently
    Katzenpost works over TCP/IP however in the future we plan to
    support QUIC/IP as an optional transport that can be selected.
  </para>
  <para>
    Katzenpost uses a PQ Noise based protocol known as the Katzenpost
    wire protocol, which provides point to point transport security and
    authorization. The wire protocol enforces the mix network’s topology
    whereby the clients are only allowed to connect to gateway nodes,
    gateway nodes are only allowed to send packets to layer 1 mixes, and
    layer 1 mixes are only allowed to send packets to layer 2 mixes etc.
  </para>
  <para>
    Clients use the wire protocol to talk to gateway nodes to whom they
    send Sphinx packets. These Sphinx packets are encapsulated within
    the encrypted PQ Noise messages and are therefore never exposed to
    passive network observers but if they were there wouldn’t in
    principle be any problem with that. This redundancy in security is
    often referred to as &quot;defense in depth&quot;.
  </para>
  <para>
    Besides within the mixnet itself, the wire protocol is also used to
    directly communicate with the directory authorities. Gateway nodes
    retrieve the latest PKI document from the directory authorities and
    cache the document for the epoch duration so that clients can
    download the cached copy. This is a notably different use case
    because within the mixnet we should have the goal of padding all the
    wire protocol commands to be the same size. Whereas when gateways
    nodes download the consensus they are likely receiving PKI documents
    which are perhaps many times bigger than our Sphinx packet size.
  </para>
  <para>
    The PKI/Directory authority protocol stands apart from the rest
    because it’s the root of all authority within the mix network. The
    PKI provides the network participants with all the connection
    information and key materials they need to use the other two
    protocols, PQ Noise and Sphinx. It does so by publishing a PKI
    document every epoch (currently 20 minutes). This is necessary
    because the mixes destroy their old mix keys and create new mix keys
    for each new epoch thereby reducing the window for compulsion
    attacks to the epoch duration.
  </para>
  <para>
    Both the PQ Noise based wire protocol AND our Sphinx protocols are
    considered to be transport protocols. However the dirauth as the 3rd
    cryptographic protocol here refers to two aspects:
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        The client and mixnet interactions with the dirauth system; That
        is, the pki document itself it signed by a majority of the
        dirauth nodes AND the pki document contains the mix descriptor
        for each mix node in the network. The document also specifies
        the topology. Mix nodes and clients verify these cryptographic
        signatures.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        The dirauth’s crash fault consensus cryptographic protocol for
        publishing new PKI documents every epoch.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
</section>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="katzenpost-pki-directory-authority">
  <title>Katzenpost PKI / Directory Authority</title>
  <section xml:id="section-5">
    <title></title>
    <para>
      The public key infrastructure (PKI) protocol for Katzenpost, also
      known as the Directory Authority or dirauth, is a decentralized
      system of nodes which vote for each epoch’s consensus document. If
      we used a BFT protocol instead then the dirauth system would fail
      when 1/3 + 1 nodes failed. Therefore we can say that our crash
      fault tolerant system is more robust because it will fail when 1/2
      + 1 nodes fail.
    </para>
    <para>
      The Katzenpost PKI is the security root of the entire system
      because all clients and network nodes will depend on the PKI to
      sign the consensus document for each epoch. Currently epoch
      duration is every 20 minutes. The consensus document is
      essentially a view of the network, it contains all the connection
      information and all the public cryptographic key materials and
      signatures. Each mix node signs it’s descriptor and uploads it to
      the dirauth nodes. Each dirauth node signs the consensus. When
      clients or nodes download the consensus document they are able to
      verify the dirauth node signatures on the document.
    </para>
    <para>
      Currently we use a hybrid signature scheme consisting of the
      classical Ed25519 and the post quantum stateless hash based
      signature scheme known as Sphincs+ with the parameters:
      ‘sphincs-shake-256f‘
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="the-katzenpost-noise-protocol-layer">
  <title>The Katzenpost Noise Protocol Layer</title>
  <para>
    Early versions of Katzenpost used the Noise cryptographic protocol
    framework; however we used an HFS (hybrid forward secret) variation
    of XX handshake that used a post quantum KEM however it could not
    resist active quantum adversaries since the initial keys exchanged
    were classical ECDH public keys. Such constructions offer
    protections against current classical adversaries that record
    ciphertext transcripts in hopes of breaking them in the future with
    a cryptographically relevant quantum computer.
  </para>
  <para>
    More recently, Katzenpost was made to use PQ Noise from the paper,
    entitled, Post Quantum Noise . The paper shows us that we can
    algebraically transform existing classical Noise handshake patterns
    into post quantum handshake patterns by replacing all usages of ECDH
    with KEM. In some of these transformations there’s additional
    network interactions implied.
  </para>
  <para>
    Our current, hybrid KEM uses our security preserving KEM combiner
    and the NIKE to KEM adapter (ad hoc hashed el gamal construction).
    Our Noise protocol string is:
  </para>
  <para>
    Noise_pqXX_Kyber768X25519_ChaChaPoly_BLAKE2b
  </para>
  <para>
    Which means that our PQ Noise protocol uses the following
    cryptographic primitives:
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Hybrid KEM: KEM Combiner + NIKE to KEM adapter + X25519 +
        Kyber768
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        MAC: Blake2b
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        AEAD: ChaChaPoly
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
<literallayout>We use the PQ Noise handshake pattern known as pqXX
which is expressed in the PQ Noise pattern language like so:</literallayout>
  <blockquote>
<literallayout>-&gt; e
&lt;- ekem, s
-&gt; skem, s
&lt;- skem
</literallayout>
  </blockquote>
  <para>
    Expressed as a sequence diagram, pqXX looks like this:
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Client sends there ephemeral public key (e).
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Server sends it’s static public key (s), encrypted with the KEM
        ciphertext (ekem) keyed to client’s public ephemeral key.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Client sends their static public key (s) encapsulated via KEM
        ciphertext (skem) keyed to server’s static public key.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Server sends a KEM ciphertext (skem) encapsulated using the
        client’s static public key.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <section xml:id="future-improvement-option-1">
    <title>future improvement, option 1:</title>
    <para>
      Remove the &quot;retrieve message&quot; command which client’s use
      to poll for new messages. Instead the client - server Noise
      protocol should be designed such that clients periodically receive
      messages from the server without requesting or polling for them.
      If no message is present in the message queue on the server then
      the server will send the client a decoy message.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="future-improvement-option-2">
    <title>future improvement, option 2:</title>
    <para>
      Replace the &quot;retrieve message&quot; command with a &quot;send
      and retrieve&quot; command whereby every time the client sends a
      message they also receive a message. As per usual, perhaps some of
      the messages send and received are decoy messages.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="classical-sphinx-and-post-quantum-sphinx">
  <title>Classical Sphinx and Post Quantum Sphinx</title>
  <para>
    The original Sphinx paper introduces the Sphinx nested encrypted
    packet format using a NIKE
    <link linkend="fn3" id="fnref3" role="footnote-ref"><superscript>3</superscript></link>.
    NIKE Sphinx can be a hybrid post quantum construction simply by
    using a hybrid NIKE. Our Sphinx implementation also can optionally
    use a KEM
    <link linkend="fn4" id="fnref4" role="footnote-ref"><superscript>4</superscript></link>
    instead of a NIKE, however the trade-off is that the packet’s header
    will take up a lot of overhead because it must store a KEM
    ciphertext for each hop. Katzenpost has a completely configurable
    Sphinx geometry which allows for any KEM or NIKE to be used.
  </para>
<literallayout>The Sphinx cryptographic packet format also uses these additional cryptographic primitives, the current Katzenpost selection is:
</literallayout>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        stream cipher: CTR-AES256
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        MAC: HMAC-SHA256
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        KDF: HKDF-SHA256
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        SPRP: AEZv5
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
    In Katzenpost the dirauths select the Sphinx geometry, each dirauth
    must agree with the other dirauths. They publish the hash of the
    Sphinx Geometry in the PKI document so that the rest of the network
    entities can validate their Sphinx Geometry. At the time of writing
    the namenlos network still uses classical Sphinx with the following
    geometry:
  </para>
  <figure>
    <title></title>
<literallayout>
PacketLength = 3082
NrHops = 5
HeaderLength = 476
RoutingInfoLength = 410
PerHopRoutingInfoLength = 82
SURBLength = 572
SphinxPlaintextHeaderLength = 2
PayloadTagLength = 32
ForwardPayloadLength = 2574
UserForwardPayloadLength = 2000
NextNodeHopLength = 65
SPRPKeyMaterialLength = 64
NIKEName = &quot;x25519&quot;
KEMName = &quot;&quot;
</literallayout>
  </figure>
  <para>
    In the Katzenpost implementation of Sphinx, we MAC an unencrypted
    two byte region at the beginning of the Sphinx packet; This
    additional data region is to be used to match Sphinx version
    numbers.
  </para>
</section>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="mixnet-attack-trees">
  <title>Mixnet Attack Trees</title>
  <figure>
    <title>attacker’s goal is to compromise a mix node</title>
    <para>
      Compromise Mix Node physical Access compromise human operator
      social engineering threat of violence blackmail large money bribe
      legal action police action military action compromise software
      remote code execution vulnerability compromise software upgrade
      pipeline malware USB stick mail interdiction evil maid attack
    </para>
  </figure>
  <para>
    The above attack tree consists of all OR nodes because each of the
    leaves are alternative ways to achieve the sub-goal expressed by
    their branch which in turn, each branch, e.g. physical access,
    compromise human operator, compromise software are each alternatives
    to the overall goal of compromising the mix node.
  </para>
  <para>
    ,,,, ,,
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para xml:id="fn1">
        Sphinx Single Use Reply Block is essentially a one-time use
        privacy preserving delivery
        token<link linkend="fnref1" role="footnote-back">↩︎</link>
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para xml:id="fn2">
        Automatic Repeat reQuest is a category network error correction
        strategies that uses retransmissions and acknowledgement
        packets<link linkend="fnref2" role="footnote-back">↩︎</link>
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para xml:id="fn3">
        NIKE: non-interactive key
        exchange<link linkend="fnref3" role="footnote-back">↩︎</link>
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para xml:id="fn4">
        KEM: key encapsulation
        mechanism<link linkend="fnref4" role="footnote-back">↩︎</link>
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
</section>
